Finding Aid for James B. Angell Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Addresses and Articles, 1849-1914; 2.6 linear feet
  - 1859
    - Family Blessings, address on Home Culture, in the Richmond St. Congregational Church, Providence, March 21; outline of speech on The Acts, June 9, 1867 (Box 8)
      (311)
    - Fourth of July Oration. (Box 8)
      (312)
  - 1859-1912
    - National Wit and Humor, lecture given on various occasions. (Box 8)
      (313)
  - 1865-1866
    - "What We Have Been Learning and Teaching" (Box 8)
      (314)
  - 1867
    - Address to the University of Vermont Medical Class of 1867 (Box 8)
      (and with modifications also given to the U-M Medical Class of 1873)
      (315)
    - Baccalaureate, University of Vermont. (Box 8)
      (316)
  - 1868
    - Address to the Alumni of Brown University. (Box 8)
      (317)
  - 1869
    - Review of Lechler's Commentary of the Acts; read before ? Association, May 17. (Box 8)
      (318)
    - Baccalaureate Address (and with changes also given to the U-M graduating class of 1872) (Box 8)
      (319)
  - 1867-1871
    (various dates delivered)
    - "Alone or With the Majority" (Box 8)
      (320)
  - 1870
    - Speech on Decoration Day to Soldiers of the G.A.R., Burlington, May 30. (Box 8)
      (321)
    - Baccalaureate Discourse, July 31. (Box 8)
      (322)
    - "The Permanent Elements of Puritanism," address given at Vermont Congregational Convention, June. (Box 8)
      (323)
  - 1871
    - Address to Dairymen's Association, Burlington, January 18. (Box 8)
      (324)
    - Baccalaureate at the University of Vermont. (Box 8)
      (325)
    - Inaugural Address, University of Michigan, June 28. (Box 8)
      (326)
  - 1874
    - "Christianity as a Life," Address to Y.M.C.A., Ann Arbor. (Box 8)
      (327)
    - "Christianity--A Privilege not a Burden," address in University Hall, Sunday Discourse, November. (Box 8)
      (328)
  - 1875
    - Re international law (Box 8)
      (282)
      (in box 7)
    - Unspecified (Box 8)
      (283)
    - Re. death of U.S. Grant (Box 8)
      (284)
    - "The Permanent Power of the Pulpit" read before State Congregational Convention, Kalamazoo. (Box 8)
      (329)
    - Baccalaureate Discourse, June 27. (Box 8)
      (330)
    - "The Manliness of the Christian Life," November (Box 8)
      (331)
  - 1876
    - "Honor in Private and in Public Life," Baccalaureates of 1876, 1889 (Box 8)
      (332)
    - "Christian Ideal of Duty and Pleasure," University Hall, October 29. (Box 8)
      (333)
    - "The Denominational Colleges and the University," read before the Michigan State Teachers' Association, December (Box 8)
      (334)
  - 1877
    - "Relation of American Colleges to Christianity," Evangelical Alliance, Detroit, November 1. (Box 8)
      (335)
    - "The Expanding Power of Christianity," November 11. (Box 8)
      (336)
  - 1878
    - "Christianity: the Future Religion of the Race," Baccalaureate. (Box 8)
      (337)
    - "Reflex Influence of the Teacher's Profession," given before the Illinois State Teacher's Association. (Box 8)
      (338)
  - 1878-1879
    - "Christianity and the Labor Problem," read in Detroit. (Box 8)
      (339)
  - 1879
    - "Duty of Allegiance," given on Fast Day as a Chapel Talk, January 23. (Box 8)
      (340)
    - "The Higher Education," Commencement Address, University of Michigan, June 26. (Box 8)
      (341)
    - Address to the Legislative Session of 1879. (Box 8)
      (342)
  - 1880
    - "History of the American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions" given in the Congregational Church, Ann Arbor, January 4 (Box 8)
      (343)
    - "The Cultivation of Character" given in University Hall, January 11 (Box 8)
      (also the Baccalaureate in 1894)
      (344)
    - Speech to the Convention of Agricultural Societies, Ann Arbor, Court House, January 21 (Box 8)
      (345)
  - 1882-1892
    - "China and the Chinese," notes for lecture; "Peking and its Environs," lecture, 1882-1890 (Box 8)
      (346)
  - 1882
    - Speech given at Jackson Convention of State Charities and Correction, December 5 (Box 8)
      (347)
  - 1883
    - Address at Dr. B. F. Cocker's Funeral at the Methodist Church, Ann Arbor, April 10 (Box 8)
      (348)
    - "The Reproductive Power of Goodness," Baccalaureate (Box 8)
      (349)
  - 1884 (Box 9)
    - "The Search after Moral and Spiritual Truth," Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (350)
    - "Relations of Western Powers to China and Japan," July 15 (Box 9)
      (351)
    - Interview with Chinese Gordon, dated August 19 (Box 9)
      (352)
  - 1885
    - "Let No Man Despise Thy Youth," discourse to the Graduating Classes of 1885. (Box 9)
      (353)
    - Address at the Memorial Service to Ulysses S. Grant, August (Box 9)
      (354)
    - "Balkan Troubles," given at the Political Science Association, November 7; "Balkan States," undated; "The Recent Riots in Serbia," Summer School, 1903 (Box 9)
      (355)
    - Address presenting Memorial Record to Welch Post, G.A.R., November 20 (Box 9)
      (356)
  - 1886
    - "What Education is needed in Michigan," given at Battle Creek High School Commencement (Box 9)
      (357)
    - Address given at Michigan Semi-Centennial, June 15 (Box 9)
      (358)
    - "Stir Up the Gift of God Which is In Thee," Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (359)
    - "France, China, and Vatican," for the Congregationalist, December 21 (Box 9)
      (360)
    - "Co-Education," for symposium in Baptist Quarterly, December (Box 9)
      (361)
    - Address at the Dedication of the Coldwater Library, December 29 (Box 9)
      (362)
  - 1887
    - Remarks at the Funeral of Professor Edward Olney, January 20 (Box 9)
      (363)
    - "The Relations of Christianity to Business," lecture at Newton Seminary, Spring (Box 9)
      (364)
    - "The Relations of Christianity to Government," lecture at Newton Seminary, Spring (Box 9)
      (365)
    - Commemorative Oration for the Semi-Centennial Celebration, University of Michigan (Box 9)
      (366)
  - 1888
    - Remarks at the laying of the corner-stone of the Student's Christian Association, May 26 (Box 9)
      (367)
    - "Propulsive Forces in Christian Life," Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (368)
    - Outline for Recall of Minister, given to Political Science Association, December 19 (Box 9)
      (369)
  - 1889
    - "State Universities: Their Difficulties, Their Advantages, Their Needs," address at University of Nebraska, February 15. (Box 9)
      (370)
    - Comments on the Nineteenth Century discussions on examinations, June 18 (Box 9)
      (371)
    - "American Rights in the Bering Sea," articles published in The Forum, November (Box 9)
      (372)
    - Remarks on Dr. Henry S. Frieze, made at Senate meeting, December 7 (Box 9)
      (373)
    - Speech on the Mayflower Compact, Detroit, December 17 (Box 9)
      (374)
  - 1890
    - The Heroic Spirit in Life, Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (375)
    - Speech of welcome to National Music Teachers' Association, Detroit, July 1 (Box 9)
      (376)
  - 1891
    - "The Development of State Universities," given at the 25th anniversary of Kansas University (Box 9)
      (377)
    - "Leadership through Self-Surrender," Baccalaureate, 1891 (Box 9)
      (378)
    - Address before Congregational State Association (Box 9)
      (379)
  - 1892
    - "The Thinker and the Doer," Commencement Address at South Bend High School (Box 9)
      (380)
  - 1893
    - "The State Universities of the West," address at the 17th anniversary celebration, John Hopkins University, February 22 (Box 9)
      (381)
    - Lessons from the Life of St. Paul, Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (382)
    - "The Inadequate Recognition of American Historical Association, Chicago," July 11. (Box 9)
      (383)
  - 1893-1894
    - Unidentified address on public support of secondary and higher education. (Box 9)
      (384)
  - 1894
    - Outline of speech at Brown University Alumni Meeting, March 9 (Box 9)
      (385)
    - Reply to the inquiry by the Royal Commission on Secondary Education, July 10. (Box 9)
      (386)
  - 1895
    - Outline of speech delivered at dedication of Kirkwood Hall, Indiana University, January 25. (Box 9)
      (387)
    - Remarks made at the presentation of the Thomas M. Cooley bust to the University, May 24. (Box 9)
      (388)
    - "State Universities," Dedication Address at the University of Missouri of their new buildings. (Box 9)
      (389)
    - "The Problem of Equipoise in Life," Baccalaureate (Box 9)
      (390)
  - 1896
    - Outline of speech to the Farmer's Institute, Ypsilanti, January 3 (Box 9)
      (391)
    - Speech at Arbitration Conference, Washington, April 22. (Box 9)
      (392)
    - Speech at celebration of 25 years of his presidency, June (Box 9)
      (393)
    - Address on the unveiling of bust of T.D. Gilbert, June 5. (Box 9)
      (394)
    - "Patriotism and International Brotherhood," Baccalaureate. (Box 9)
      (395)
    - Address at the Inter-Collegiate Association of North Central States. (Box 9)
      (396)
  - 1897
    - "Ambitions and Ideals," Baccalaureate Address. (Box 9)
      (397)
    - Speech given at the Commercial Club of Chicago--dedication of the Crerar Library, circa 1897 (Box 9)
      (398)
  - 1898
    - Two Egyptian Universities, published in the Michiganensian. (Box 9)
      (399)
    - Address to graduation class Scutari Women's College. (Box 9)
      (400)
    - Address at the Peace Jubilee on International Arbitration, Chicago, October. (Box 9)
      (401)
    - Outlines for speeches, Scientific Club, Dec 3 1898 and Graduate Club, May 26, 1899 (Box 9)
      (402)
    - Memorial Service for Rowland Hazard of Peace Dale, Rhode Island, December 31 (Box 9)
      (403)
    - Ministers and Ambassadors outline of speech; outlines of speeches on consular reform, undated (Box 9)
      (404)
  - 1898, 1904; 1909
    - Notes and outlines for speeches on the Balkan countries (Box 9)
      (405)
  - 1899
    - "Is There a Surplus of College Bred Men," article written for Youth's Companion (Box 9)
      (406)
    - "Our Diplomatic and Consular Service," address at Colgate University, April 21 (Box 9)
      (407)
    - "The Eastern Question." (Box 9)
      (408)
    - "The Debt of the University Graduate," Baccalaureate. (Box 9)
      (409)
    - "The Old College and the New University," Founder's Day Address at the University of Chicago, July 1. (Box 9)
      (410)
    - President's Address to the International Congregational Council, Boston, September 20. (Box 9)
      (411)
    - Address at Wellesley College on the occasion of the inauguration of Caroline Hazard, October 3. (Box 10)
      (412)
    - "The Dismemberment of China," address to Business Men's Class, Congregational Church of Ann Arbor, December 17. (Box 10)
      (413)
  - 1900
    - "Present Problems in the Relations of Missions to Governments," Ecumenical Council, New York, April 25. (Box 10)
      (414)
    - "The Choice of a Calling," A Swing-out Talk, published in the Saturday Evening Post, May 26. (Box 10)
      (415)
    - Swing-out Talks to graduating classes, 1900-1909 (Box 10)
      (416)
    - "The Widening Horizon," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (417)
    - Welcome to the Historical and Economic Associations, December (Box 10)
      (418)
  - 1901
    - Burke A. Hinsdale, a paper written for the Education Review, February (Box 10)
      (419)
    - "Moral Responsibilities and Opportunities of Secondary Teachers," (Box 10)
      (420)
    - "Environment and Selfhood," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (421)
    - Welcome to the National Education Association, Detroit. (Box 10)
      (422)
    - Speech given at the Bicentenary of Detroit, July 24. (Box 10)
      (423)
    - Address to Women's Clubs, University Hall, October (Box 10)
      (424)
  - 1902
    - "Progress of International Law and Diplomacy," given at the First Congregational Church of Detroit, April 6. (Box 10)
      (425)
    - "The New Era in Higher Education," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (426)
    - "Reminiscences of College Life from 1845-1849," for Brown University Souvenir, September (Box 10)
      (427)
    - Greetings at the Inauguration of President James, Northwestern University, October; and at his inauguration at the University of Illinois, 1905 (Box 10)
      (428)
  - 1903
    - President Charles Kendall Adams in early life and at the University of Michigan address at the University of Wisconsin, January (Box 10)
      (429)
    - Remarks to Commission on Religious Education, Chicago, January (Box 10)
      (430)
    - Alice Freeman Palmer, Memorial Address at Cambridge, January 31. (Box 10)
      (431)
    - Address given at the Alice Freeman Palmer Memorial Service, Chicago, February 11. (Box 10)
      (432)
    - Lessons Suggested by Christ's Life to the Scholar, Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (433)
    - Talk to students at the opening of the school term, October (Box 10)
      (434)
    - Reminiscences of Providence Journal, November 3. (Box 10)
      (435)
    - Outline of Address to the Modern Language Association, December (Box 10)
      (436)
  - 1904
    - Address, Charter Day of the University of California, March 23. (Box 10)
      (437)
    - "Knowledge and Wisdom" Baccalaureate address, June 19 (Box 10)
      (438)
    - Address at the opening of the Hackley Hospital, Muskegon, November 17. (Box 10)
      (439)
    - Current International Questions, given at Scientific Club, December 3. (Box 10)
      (440)
    - Outline of speech to the State Teachers' Association, December (Box 10)
      (441)
    - Outline of talks to the Students' Christian Association, 1904; 1908; undated (Box 10)
      (442)
    - Speech at dedication of Grand Rapids Library. (Box 10)
      (443)
  - 1905
    - Speech given at the opening of a Carnegie Library in Manistee, April 28. (Box 10)
      (444)
    - "The Old and the New Ideal of Scholars," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (445)
    - "The European Concert and the Monroe Doctrine," address to Phi Beta Kappa, Harvard, June 28. (Box 10)
      (446)
    - Remarks at Harvard Commencement Dinner, June 28. (Box 10)
      (447)
    - Speech given at a Phi Beta Kappa dinner at Harvard, June 29. (Box 10)
      (448)
    - Outline of speech to the Women's League, November 3. (Box 10)
      (449)
    - Welcome to Scientific Societies, Christmas. (Box 10)
      (450)
  - 1906
    - Speech at the Memorial Service for Dr. William J. Herdman. (Box 10)
      (451)
    - Outline of speech at Brown Alumnae Rally. (Box 10)
      (452)
    - "Honesty," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (453)
    - Manuscript article about History of the University of Michigan by Prof. Burke A. Hinsdale, edited by Prof. Isaac N. Demmon, and published by the University of Michigan in, appeared in the Michigan Alumnus, October, 1906 (Box 10)
      (454)
    - Speech given at the laying of the corner-stone, Sorosis House, June. (Box 10)
      (455)
    - Address at presentation of portrait of Angell to the University of Michigan. (Box 10)
      (456)
  - 1907
    - Address to Michigan Agricultural College, May. (Box 10)
      (457)
    - "The Spiritual Opportunities of Secular Education," given at Convention of the Congregational Brotherhood, Detroit. (Box 10)
      (458)
    - Outline and notes used at the dedication of the Calumet High School, November 22. (Box 10)
      (459)
  - 1908
    - "The Age of Quickened Conscience," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (460)
    - Outline on Hague Conference Lecture Service. (Box 10)
      (461)
  - 1909
    - "The State and the Student," Baccalaureate. (Box 10)
      (462)
    - Speech at dedication of the John N. Hazard Guild House, September 11. (Box 10)
      (463)
    - Remarks made at a "Supper" on the occasion of the inauguration of President Nichols of Dartmouth, October 14. (Box 10)
      (464)
  - 1910
    - "The Honest Engineer," commencement address at the Armour Institute, May 26. (Box 10)
      (465)
    - Memorial Address for Mrs. Eliza Read Sunderland, Ann Arbor, May 29. (Box 10)
      (466)
    - Address given at the dedication of the John Hay Library, Brown University, November 11. (Box 10)
      (467)
    - "The Dorr War," (Rhode Island History) given at "The Two Clubs," June 11. (Box 10)
      (468)
    - Address; last swing-out address. (Box 10)
      (469)
  - 1911
    - "The Influence of the Lawyer Outside of his Profession," Washington's Birthday Address to Law Students. (Box 10)
      (470)
  - 1913
    - Speech at the dedication of Hill Auditorium. (Box 10)
      (471)
    - Outlines for lectures on China, 1913; 1914 (Box 10)
      (472)
  - 1914
    - Remarks made at the Baccalaureate Exercises. (Box 10)
      (473)
    - "Reminiscences of Whistler,", undated (Box 10)
      (474)
    - Speech to Psi Upsilon Fraternity at Brown University. (Box 10)
      (475)
    - Speech, dedication of table placed on Mason Hall by D.A.R. (Box 10)
      (476)
    - Speech on "How far should a University control the students?", undated (Box 10)
      (477)
    - Obituary for Arthur Hill. (Box 10)
      (478)
    - Review of the Life of Alice Freeman Palmer (Box 10)
      (479)
- Subject Files and Personal Papers, 1845-1908; 3.4 linear feet, 1 oversize folder
  The Subject Files and Personal Papers series includes a variety of material reflecting Angell's interest and activities as well as aspects of his personal life. It includes notes and materials collected for historical research and lectures, files concerning his diplomatic missions and service on the fisheries commission, and material relating to the University of Michigan. The personal materials include several biographical sketches, a manuscript and typescript of The Reminiscences of James B. Angell and Angell's will and the inventory of his estate.
  - Lectures concerning the history of the idea of the state, November 1888; 5 folders (Box 10)
    (480-484)
  - Notes for the history of the idea of the state, 1888; 3 folders (Box 10)
    (485-487)
  - Notes on French Revolution and other historical subjects (Box 10)
    (488)
  - Lecture notes on Constitutional History-U.S. and English (Box 10)
    (489)
  - "Notes on the moral element in literature", undated (Box 10)
    (490)
  - Portions of addresses, notes, unidentified' and undated (Box 10)
    (491)
  - Abstract of Mulford's Nation, undated (Box 10)
    (492)
  - Notes on Treaty of 1783, Treaty of 1778, Jay's Treaty, Oregon boundary, notes and newspaper articles on Korea (Box 10)
    (493)
  - Sketch of General James M. Varnum for the Centennial in 1876 (Box 10)
    (494)
  - Notes on international law, 5 folders (Box 11)
    (495-499)
  - The reminiscences of James B. Angell (Manuscript and typescript), 9 folders (Box 11)
    (500-508)
  - Finances, tables, and charts-the University of Michigan (Box 11)
    (509)
  - High School material (Box 11)
    (510)
  - Fisheries Commission
    - Printed matter, 1886-1887 (Box 11)
      (511)
    - Printed matter, 1887 (Box 11)
      (512)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      (513)
    - Notes and papers on fisheries controversy (Box 11)
      (514)
    - Clippings on Fisheries Commission and Fisheries Treaty (Box 11)
      (515)
  - Confidential report on the Drogoman at the American Legation at Constantinople in 1898 (Box 11)
    (516)
  - Miscellanea relating to Turkey (Box 11)
    (517)
  - Printed matter relating to the Chinese Treaty (Box 11)
    (518)
  - Pamphlets relating to opium (Box 11)
    (519)
  - Manuscripts and newspaper clippings about opium (Box 11)
    (520)
  - Clippings on visit of International American Congress to Ann Arbor, October 17, 1889 (Box 11)
    (521)
  - Clippings on international arbitration (Box 11)
    (522)
  - Clippings on arbitration; China, and Spanish-American War (Box 11)
    (523)
  - Clippings on Bering Sea (Box 11)
    (524)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 11)
    (525)
  - Will of James B. Angell and inventory of estate (Box 12)
    (526)
  - Biographical sketch of James B. Angell (Box 12)
    (527)
  - Papers regarding the Thompson Estate (Mrs. Angell family), 2 folders (Box 12)
    (528-529)
  - Information regarding nominees for secretaryship of the Smithsonian Institute (Box 12)
    (530)
  - Supreme Court records pertaining to Chinese Exclusion Act (Box 12)
    (531)
  - Papers and accounts for Shakespeare Fund (Box 12)
    (532)
  - Resolutions passed by Student Council on death of President Angell, 1916 (Box 12)
    (533)
  - Riddles in verse (Box 12)
    (534)
  - Waterman Gymnasium Fund (Box 12)
    (file donated by donor nos. 2716 and 2942)
    (535)
  - Notes and printed matter on the Panama Canal (Box 12)
    (536)
  - Printed items from Angell scrapbook (Box 12)
    (537)
  - Notes on United States Treaties (Box 12)
    (538)
  - Records (includes clippings) of University of Michigan alumni in the mission field (Box 12)
    (539)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 12)
    (540)
  - Miscellaneous notes and biographical material (Box 12)
    (541)
  - U.S. Deep Water Commission
    - American Shipbuilding and Lake Transportation, 1891 (Box 12)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Private Circulation, October 16, 1895 (Box 12)
    - Basin of the Great Lakes and of the St. Lawrence and Hudson Rivers (Box 12)
    - The Canals of Canada, 1894 (Box 12)
    - Conclusions (Box 12)
    - Corthell on An Enlarged Water-Way, 1891 (Box 12)
    - Detroit Session Deep Waterways Commission (Box 12)
    - Effects of Gales on Lake Erie, 1896 (Box 12)
    - Elevations for the Great Lakes and for the Saint Lawrence and Hudson Rivers, September 1896 (Box 12)
    - Exhibits, March 31, 1896 (Box 12)
    - The Future of Chicago and Illinois, January 1, 1887 (Box 12)
    - The Ice Season, December 1896 (Box 12)
    - International Deep Waterways Association Proceedings, 1895 (Box 12)
    - The Lake and Gulf Waterway, 1888 (Box 12)
    - Lake Level Effects on Account of the Main Channel of the Sanitary District of Chicago, 1895 (Box 12)
    - The Lakes and Atlantic Waterway, August 1896 (Box 12)
    - The Lakes and Gulf Waterways as Related to the Chicago Sanitary Problem (Box 12)
    - Maps, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Mr. Brice, from the Committee on Interstate Commerce, Report, 1889 (Box 12)
    - A Plea in Behalf of the South and West for Deep Water at Savannah, Georgia, 1891 (Box 12)
    - Progress Report
      - March, 31, 1896 (Box 12)
      - April 30, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, May 31, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, June 30, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, July 31, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, August 31, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, September 30, 1896 (Box 12)
      - Engineering, January 8, 1897 (Box 12)
    - Proceedings of the Deep Waterways Convention, 1894 (Box 12)
    - Report on Special Reconnaissance Near International Boundry, May 5, 1856 (Box 12)
    - Reorganization of National Public Works Part 1, March 1888 (Box 12)
    - Report on the Internal Commerce of the United States, 1891 (Box 12)
    - Report on Oswego-Oneida-Mohawk Routes, May 20, 1896 (Box 12)
    - Report on Special Work, November 1896 (Box 12)
    - Saint Lawrence - Champlain Route Special Report on Preliminary Reconnaissances, August 1896 (Box 12)
    - Sanitary District of Chicago
      - President's Annual Message, 1894 (Box 12)
      - Proceedings of the Board of Trustees, September 14, 1892 (Box 12)
      - Report, 1894-1895 (Box 12)
    - Schedule of Topics Prepared for Deep Waterways Commission, December 31, 1896 (Box 12)
    - Tables of Water Levels for the Great Lakes and Saint Lawrence River, 1896 (Box 12)
    - The Twenty Foot Channel, 1891 (Box 12)
    - Water Levels for the Great Lakes and Saint Lawrence River
      - May 1896 (Box 12)
      - November 1896 (Box 12)
  - Passport (Box 13)
    (543)
  - Autograph book (Box 13)
    (543 A)
  - Notebook (Box 13)
    (542B)
  - Account book, 1845-1846 (Box 13)
    (544)
  - Diaries